Welcome to Launched. I'm Charlie Chapman
and today I'm excited to bring you the
developer behind the new iOS game, The
Art of Fauna, Clemens Strasser.
[Music]
Clemens, welcome to the show. Thank you
for having me. It's uh it's been fun.
We've hung out relatively recently uh in
random parts of the world. Uh and you've
like I I I'm starting to think it's like
a a meme to only myself at this point
that I start the show with you've been
on my list forever, but that's because I
haven't been doing episodes enough. So,
everybody's been on my list forever. Uh
but I'm very excited to have you on. I
feel like uh you kind of hit another
like niche. I haven't had like a game
indie game developer on in a while. uh
maybe since like Ryan with Blackbox.
Yeah. Uh so there's a whole it's a whole
different kind of world but obviously
overlapping a lot. So I'm excited to get
into that. Yeah. I'm super happy to be
here. I'm listening to Launch for a very
very long time. So I didn't think that I
will ever be in an episode. So I'm very
excited.
Awesome. Well uh before we get into all
of your games, uh I want to give
everybody kind of an introduction into
who you are. So, the three questions I
always ask to kick off this show is
where are you from? Uh, do you have a
formal education related to what you do?
And then we can kind of talk about what
your career was leading into the sort of
indie uh game dev that you're doing now.
So, I'm from Gratz, Austria. I I'm
basically born and uh raised here or
around that area. So, not too far away.
I actually grew up in a very small
village um like couple of 2 hours away
something like that um from here but
then uh moved to a smaller town near
Gratz and now live in Gratz for 8 years
and yes I do have a formal education. I
did do my uh first we we in Austria have
something like a technical high school
thing and I did learn to program there.
So, this is part of like primary school
or is it like post normal school? Like
this is an optional thing. Just curious.
No. Um I mean I'm I'm not even sure how
that relates to to US school years, but
it's like when I turn turned 13, I went
to that school. So I think it's school.
So yeah, that yeah, that tracks. So it's
um I think when you're 14 in Austria,
you have to do one more year of uh
education and then you could do
something else. But uh basically most
most people actually finish or or most
people is also not not completely true
but many people um then do high school
here and um for me the choice was that
uh technical school it's one year longer
than the other education but you get uh
taught more the technical stuff and like
electrical engineering was big part of
that but also programming and um so I
learned to program in C and in like very
uh languages that are close to hardware
first and then moved on to some higher
level stuff and nice after that um I
went to university here in gratz and uh
did a bachelor's and masters in computer
science and while I was doing my um my
bachelor's I started programming iOS and
then kind of got into all of that.
That's interesting. Like I just from
following you for a long time, I kind of
assumed that your background was in
design. Uh cuz that seems to be a big
part of like your focus and and what you
like lean really heavily on. Yeah. Yeah.
And it's it's interesting because I'm I
was never taught anything design-wise. I
never worked the design job or did
anything along those lines. I um I'm a
computer programmer by trade and that's
basically what I always did. Nice. So,
okay. So, you have you have that degree
then. Uh and then you went into the
field and started programming. Was it
like mobile or iOS work at the beginning
or Yeah. What were you doing? So, so I
was um I was currently I was doing my
bachelor's and um the the one of the
things that I had to learn um during my
bachelors in at university was regular
expressions and um I did not really
enjoy how they were taught at
university. So, I thought I could make
something more interesting out of that.
And uh always wanted to um start
learning how to program for iOS. I
didn't own an iPhone or anything like
that, but I owned a Mac and I had an
iPod touch and I wanted to do something
because the the platform very was very
interesting to me. And so, I thought I'm
going to do a crossword type puzzle game
around regular expressions. And so that
thing could teach me both how regular
expressions really work and also how to
do Objective C programming. That was in
2014 where we didn't have Swift yet. So
early 2014. And so I started to learn
all of that. And then when I had my exam
um about regular expressions, I uh I
made that exam. So that uh worked out
very well. So, I knew how to work with
them afterwards. But the the game that I
built wasn't super exciting to me
anymore. So, I stopped working on that.
A cross word puzzle about regular
expressions wasn't just taking the world
by storm. Yeah. I I I mean, the New York
Times is bound to uh you know, add that
any day now.
Uh I was super into the idea at first
and then afterwards I thought yeah this
this is not the sup most interesting
thing in the world. So I just stopped
working on that because it didn't have
anything that really excited me or
catched me. And um and then basically a
couple of uh weeks or months went by and
I uh was sitting at my couch at home and
was staring at my watch. It was a
mechanical watch back at the time
because the Apple Watch wasn't announced
yet and we knew that that thing is going
to come out at some point of time, but
we didn't exactly know when. So there
were bunch of rumors around that. And I
was looking at my watch and had this
idea of having like a very simple quiz
game where you have just statements that
are right or wrong and you swipe up or
down to say if it's correct or wrong. So
a calculation like 1 + 1 is two, you
would swipe up because it's right or a
statement about geography like Paris is
the capital of Germany and you would
swipe down because that's not right. And
I thought uh just a super simple
quiz-like game. you get one minute and
have to solve as many questions as
possible. Uh would be kind of
interesting for the Apple Watch, but as
I said, wasn't announced. So I thought I
just do it for the iPhone and then can
easily port that to the Apple Watch.
Wasn't super easy. Um when we got the
SDK, we didn't have UI kit on uh on the
Apple Watch. So that um the the whole
thing needed a a bigger rewrite than I
expected initially. But but you built
the you built the whole thing for iOS.
Did you release that? Yes, I did release
that as an iOS app. Uh it was called
Elementary Minute and that was the the
first thing that I put on the on the app
store. I released it on 1st of December
in 2014. Um, I chose that date because
in Austria if you have a business you
have to pay a certain fee to a
government thing um, which is 100 bucks
a year and you don't have to pay that
when you do that on uh, in December. So
I shifted the launch to the first of
December because I thought I'm never
going to make that those 100 bucks with
the app anyway. So I can just avoid
paying it for one year. and so released
it um for for iOS and then in the
meantime Apple Watch was announced. I
think we got the SDK in February of the
following year. Well, before that, how
did the how was it received? Like, did
anybody pick it up? Was it making money?
Like, so it was not making lots of
money. So, it was I don't know like uh
it was sold for 99 cents and it got like
one or two downloads per day, but it was
still nice especially. Yeah, that's
enough to make up your hundred bucks uh
if it kept up. Yeah. Yeah. And
especially um like the first couple of
days I saw mostly people in Austria
download it. So, I knew that those
people are probably my friends, but then
people from uh from the US downloaded it
and I didn't know anybody from the US
back then or people from China or from
other places in the world just
downloaded it. And that was just an
amazing feeling that somebody else in
the world is just playing my little game
that I made in my bedroom. It never gets
old. Yeah. There's something about it
being people you have no idea who they
are. That something you do had some
impact on their life and you have a
little string on a website that proves
that that happened. Uh something about
that is just magical. Yeah, that's
that's like really really insane to me
that things like that are possible. And
yeah, that that was a super good feeling
and uh super nice and the the whole
release. Um, for me it went well because
uh, yeah, people were actually playing
it and um, but it didn't bring in enough
money to uh, cover all my my spendings
and so I continue but I it didn't have
to anyway because I was studying and I
didn't have uh to to um, pay for my flat
or anything at that point of time. And
so I um continued working on it because
it was just fun working on it. And uh we
got the SDK for the Apple Watch in
February. And I had the the goal to
release the game for the Apple Watch
launch in April, I think it was. And be
part of Day One. Be part of Day One. and
then sent out some some press emails
before that and some trailers and that
those things got picked up and uh
generated a bit more downloads and then
actually was part of day one. I think
there were like four or five games uh on
the Apple Watch on day one and one of
those were elementary minute and that
was very nice. Uh thing is I didn't know
that it's like playing games on the
Apple Watch is not so the most fun
experience because you have to uh stand
there and hold your hand like this and
Yeah. Cuz you'd only been able to build
it in the simulator, right? Exactly. I I
was not even be able to buy an Apple
Watch on day one because it was only
released in the US first. Oh
yeah. And then then it got released a
couple of months later in Germany and I
think Austria only got it at the end of
the year. So, uh very very late. Did you
did you drive over to Germany or did you
wait for it to come to Austria? I did um
drive over to Germany to buy mine in I
think September, something like that or
or August. Yeah. Um we had to the
edition watch I assume, right? The gold.
Yeah, definitely. $10,000 one or
whatever. Yeah, I assume. Yeah. Yeah.
what you're wearing right now cuz it's
timeless.
Yeah. I I think I never saw that thing
uh life anywhere. So I No, no, I don't I
don't think there were I think the vast
majority of them were given to
celebrities. That was my impression.
Johnny IV has like 12 obviously. Yeah,
definitely.
Yeah. But then um it got it released and
that generated some uh more attention
for it because it was featured in bunch
of uh Apple Watch release stories. Then
I got my first feature from Apple um
which was a 20 under 20 feature where
they featured apps made by people who
were 20 years or younger. Oh, nice. Was
that for the Apple Watch specifically?
It was not not for the Apple Watch, but
I think Apple only got aware of me
because of that. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
Yeah. And uh Vit from Lookup was also in
that list, which was Oh, nice.
We only discovered that or I only
remembered that we both were in that
list I think last year when we were
sitting uh at uh Indian place um to have
dinner together at DUPDC and it was like
super interesting that 10 years after
that feature aired on the app store we
were just sitting together bumping into
each other. It's such a small world. And
Vidett uh being like the fifth guest
I've had on this show, four or six or
something, he was very very early
talking about. Uh yeah, that's cool.
Yeah, that was like that was a super
nice moment when we when I actually when
that clicked. Um so at this stage you
you know you're getting some press I
assume then downloads are increasing and
everything. Are you still in school at
this point? Yeah. Yeah. I'm like uh I
think I was in the second year or yeah I
think second year of my bachelor's and
bachelor is 3 years long and yeah I was
still studying at university at that
point and then I um got the through some
very good coincidences uh got the chance
to uh go to DUPDC this year. So I um
could fly to uh to the US to actually
join Apple at WTC which was like insane
to me. I was never traveling alone at
that point of time. I was never uh I've
never been outside of Europe at that
time and then I got the chance. Now
you're flying to California and you're
in the whirlwind. What year? What year
was this? This would have been
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. So it was the big
blowout version of Dubdub. Yeah, when it
was still in San Francisco and at
Moscone and how how was that? So I I
have only experienced WWDC as a uh a
person who was already kind of somewhat
known in the in the industry or whatever
you want to call this thing that we do.
Uh because I kind of jumped into it
right before CO and then everybody was
locked down for a long time. Yeah. Um,
so I'd already made a bunch of friends
online and I've only experienced the
postcoid version where there's only one
day. It's a small much smaller group of
people and then you sort of you have to
do a bunch of work to fill time.
Otherwise, you just sit in your hotel
room alone. But if you can do that, it's
an amazing experience. But I've heard
from people that even in the before
times, if you didn't already have a
group of people, it was sometimes still
hard to
uh like you still had to be active about
making sure you talk to people in lines
and like form friend groups or else you
had that same kind of experience. What
was that like for you? Uh for for me
like the the also being
very especially back then very shy and
not very forward speaking to to people
or or not not the person who uh just
goes up to people and talks to them. uh
was definitely a bit difficult but I
just always
um had like interesting people around
that I started to listening in and then
started to chat with them. So, so it
kind of always worked out for me and I I
think um not also in this year but
especially in the years after I was at
DWPC again in 2017, 18 and 19 and um
especially at those years I made so many
friends that I'm very good friends uh
with today. So, um it was even though I
didn't have like a big following on
Twitter or like knew many people uh over
the web, I still found people that I I
could relate with at Dubdc and those
people are now my friends. And that was
like super amazing. And yeah, especially
I got in there with um like we're we're
jumping around a bit, but uh makes sense
to talk about that now. Um I got in to
dodc in 2017 18 and 19 with a
scholarship. So, which is now called the
Swift Student Challenge, but back then
it was the the scholarship program. And
um I met so many people there who also
got a scholarship and we were um we
Apple back then paid for the for dorm
rooms near to um which were located in
the San Jose State University and you um
were always in a room with another
scholar. So somebody that uh went
through the same experience with you and
forcing you to interact with them and
then there were certain so social
gatherings where you had met other
scholars and uh a group formed there
naturally with uh whom I still have a
group chat and still interact with them.
Yeah, the Swift students uh thing even
going now and the scholar program as it
was called back then I feel like is such
a
cool thing because like I I was never
part of it but like anytime I go to
Dubdub I you can
feel those crowds of people who like
came up through that program whether
they became friends during it or even if
they were like from different years
there's a little bit of a it's almost
like being an alumni at a university
where you have this sort of camaraderie
or something like that like you all
experience this crazy whirlwind thing
that's very similar um and those
networks
like you know being an indie I mean a
big part of me starting this show was to
try and create one of these for myself
like having some kind of network
whenever you're uh whenever you're alone
working as an indie in a small town
somewhere you're not in New York or
California or whatever Uh it's so just
crazy valuable. Yeah, definitely. Uh
both in the like keeping your sanity,
but also in the like I'm running into
something weird. I just need to like
talk through it with somebody. And to
have somebody who's like, "Oh yeah, I
ran into that and here's the answer."
Just like ridiculously valuable. Yeah.
Um, so yeah, I I don't I don't ever know
like what the best advice is, but it's I
feel like when people go to these
conferences, especially developers who
are usually more often the type of
people who are not walk up and talk to
people openly, it's it's usually a more
shy, especially the indie crowd by
nature, you're like the type of people
who work alone. uh being incredibly
intentional uh to try and build those
networks even if it's awkward is I
cannot recommend it enough. Um
definitely
yeah dubdub is hard now. I think you
have to be very intentional and I'm
hoping like every year I've been hoping
that Apple does a little bit more to
like create spaces for this. Um and
again I'm hoping this year that maybe we
get a little bit more of that. But if
they don't, it's like find every event
you can be a little awkward and join
anything that you can and talk to
people. Um, and the flip side works for
people who already have the networks.
It's like, yeah, bring people in. Try to
include uh more people. If you see
somebody who looks like they're
interested in coming, invite them, you
know, that kind of thing. Cuz yeah, it's
it's a super weird experience, but and
that applies to any of these tech
conferences like Yeah. Uh, it changes
everything, I feel like. Yeah, I think
uh dubdub before was very easy because
also after the sessions people just went
to places, downloaded the new uh betas,
played around with APIs, you saw
somebody working on something that you
are also just looked at and um I don't
know that that whole kind of thing uh
created a basis for you to talk to some
stranger or if you picked up lunch at a
line and you weren't with your folks at
that moment, you immediately started
chatting to to other people who were
just grabbing lunch. Well, I have a
shared interest and a shared experience
that you can always kick off with. It's
especially nice for not Dubdub, but for
other uh conferences that are like
single track where everybody is watching
the same session. It's like you can
literally just bring up one of the
sessions and then yeah, even if the
person missed it, then they'll be like,
"Oh no, what' they talk about?" And then
you boom, you can go on on with that. So
yeah. Yeah. Yeah, that's nice. But
anyway, so yeah, you you got to go to
Dubdub. Crazy experience and then I
sidetracked you as I as I'm one to do.
Uh so it sounds like that was a valuable
experience for you. Yeah. Yeah. the
first dubdub. I mean that was really
really insane because again I did not
know any other iOS developer other than
a friend of mine who did also bit of uh
coding in grats but other than that
didn't know anybody and um then finally
or got the chance to go to the
conference and uh was looking up on
online uh what to do that you have to
stand in line for to get into the big
room for uh for the conference uh hours
before. So I uh flew to to San
Francisco. I couldn't sleep a second in
the plane. I um then went to my hotel in
in Chinatown and uh the guy at the hotel
told me that um they were over booked
and they don't didn't have a room for
me.
Which was also an interesting
experience. And the second guy uh also
arrived with me at the exact point of
time and had the same problem as I did
and they started screaming at each other
and I was just standing there and didn't
know what to do and my goodness. Yeah.
Uh was very interesting. But I then went
with that guy to the next Starbucks and
I booked another hotel and um complained
a bit that I'm super tired and yada yada
that um it's an interesting first
experience in the US and yeah, welcome
to America. Yeah. And but then the the
guy just said, "Yeah, uh let me make
your day a bit nicer. I'm actually
working with Google in the San Francisco
offices and if I want to get a tour
through the San Francisco offices of
Google and then uh he just took me to
the offices and showed me around. Oh my
gosh. You know what? That is a very
American experience, right? Brash uh
weird and then also like welcoming and
like, "Hey, let's just be friends and go
hang out together." Uh yeah, that's that
that's quite the introduction to the
stance. Yeah, but it was like that that
whole experience was like the start was
a bit weird and uh I don't know. I
didn't know where to sleep at first, but
I found the hotel. Most of the rooms
were booked because it was DC and 5,000
were in San Francisco. But I found a
place and I um went to to the Google
offices and those were super interesting
to me. uh also me coming out out of
Austria who would have never thought to
uh step foot in one of these offices and
yeah uh went to sleep and then woke up
very early I think at 4:00 a.m. or
something like that to go stand in line
for
DUPDC and um while standing in line I
saw at I think 6:00 a.m.ish something a
guy standing in front of me wearing an
Apple Watch and I said, "Hey, here's a
dollar. Could you download Elementary
minute for me so that I can actually see
if that thing is working on the Apple
Watch?" I just didn't know. I never saw
it on on a real device. And he said,
"No, don't have to give me anything. Uh,
download it." And gave me his Apple
Watch and I could play around with it.
And uh that was the first time I
actually saw it live on the watch.
Uh which was crazy. And yeah, then met a
couple of people while waiting in line
for adopt DC. Sat down to to see the
conference. Um and then I was back then
I was in touch with with a person from
Apple um who is responsible for
developer relations in Austria, Germany
and Switzerland and he always sent me
messages. So, hey, go to um go to to the
main conference or the keynote. Uh we
will meet there. And then right before
it started, he said, "No, I couldn't
make it, but we will meet up later." And
then again, state of the union. He wrote
me, "Hey, go to the state of the union."
And then, "Ah, couldn't make it, but uh
we we will meet at the Apple Design
Awards." And then went to the Apple
Design Awards and he said, "Yeah, again,
I'm sorry for time. couldn't make it,
but I definitely will see you around.
And
um then sat down at the design awards.
Um John Gillins started talking there
and um introducing the design awards and
said something about student winners.
And here's the first student winner. And
suddenly my face appeared on the screen
there. Oh my goodness. And I had no idea
at all. So you you had no clue. I had no
clue. Absolutely none. Wow. And yeah,
they got announced that Elementary
Minute got the Apple Design Award for um
for the in the student category, which
was a thing still back then. And uh it
was so mind-blowing to me especially
I've never like I said I never saw
elementary minute running on an Apple
watch before that day. I also back then
I think one thing that I never said
publicly anywhere is that I wasn't even
an iPhone user back then. So I didn't
have an iPhone. So you had did you have
an Android phone in your pocket? No, I
did not have an Android phone in my
pocket, but I I couldn't afford an
iPhone back then. So, I had an uh some
Google Nexus phone. And when I got the
chance to go to WWC, I asked my uncle to
borrow his old iPhone
4, which was had to be the guy. Yeah.
because I didn't wanted to be the guy
with the Android phone on the Apple
conference and uh was running around
with the phone always plugged into a
power bank because the battery was
broken. Yeah. And but I I had that and
like coming from that place and then
actually receiving the Apple Design
Award was insane.
Wow, that's so funny. And also
uh it was announced that I got the
design award and I was sitting there and
I didn't know if I had to go upstate up
to the stage or anything like what you
were supposed to do. Yeah. What I'm am I
supposed to do? And I was sitting next
to a stranger and asked him, "Hey, do
you know do I have to go to the stage?"
And he said, "I have no clue, but
congratulations." And um you if you see
the video you can see that it takes me a
minute to go upstage but I eventually
come there get my cube and then went off
stage and the guy from developer
relations was just standing there and
saying to my face I told you we will
meet eventually.
Well played. Yeah. Oh that's so crazy.
Yeah. He so he just nudged me into
sitting down to the Apple Design Awards
and said it before for the other events
so that it didn't feel awkward to me or
that I didn't notice that something is
on there. So, I had absolutely no clue
and then um got the design award, was
sitting down in front because we were
taking a photo later and my backpack
with my passport and like everything I I
had was still standing back at my
original place and I I didn't even
notice for for a while. And then um
after we did the photos, the guy who was
sitting next to me was still sitting
there because he was watching my
backpack and that was like super nice
also. Yeah, no kidding. So so many nice
experiences um after like the first
impression was I didn't get a room in
San Francisco, but then uh one nice
experience after the other. No kidding.
Wow. Well, I think I can say pretty
confidently that that is exactly what
most people's experience going to Dubdub
is always like. Uh all of those events
will happen to everybody. Yeah,
definitely. So, you should you should
come to California. Yeah.
That's crazy. So, that was Elementary
Minute. You're still in school. Yes. Uh
what next? Did you come out with more
games or more apps while you were in
school or does everything else kind of
happen after that? Yeah. the
um at that WTC I was standing on stage
uh next to the people from um from
Flexibits, the people who do ah
fantastical and cart because they won
the Apple Design Award for uh
Fantastical 2 that year. and we just
started chatting and exchanged emails
and um a couple of months later uh
Michael reached out to me and asked me
if I wanted to have an summer internship
with them um in I think 2016 then or
2017. Okay.
can't exactly remember but it wasn't in
the same year but bit later uh if I
wanted to join flexibits for summer
internship and I was a huge fantastical
fan back then I downloaded even though I
didn't have an iPhone I had uh had
fantastical on my Apple touch not
because I was in need of a calendar but
I just love the design of fantastical
and I downloaded a bunch of those apps
just to play around and see um the
different effects and things in there.
And then being able to actually work for
that company was like mind-blowing to
me. Wow, that's really cool. That's And
Michael uh Simmons, also a former guest
uh on on this very program. Uh oh, yeah,
that's cool. And yeah, working with the
flexibits people must have been just a
great experience of kind of seeing how
people build these uh much more
complicated than kind of what you had
been doing obviously at the time. Uh
apps and so that was after you graduated
then. No, it's also I was still in
school. So that was internship. Okay,
cool. It was um still it was an
internship and I was still in school and
I was um always working. So after the
internship I uh continued working on uh
Fantastical or at Flexibits until I
think 2021. Yeah, 2020. Okay. Um, and I
eventually quit at Flexibits to finally
finish up my master thesis because I
went I had a point where I um first I
only worked a couple of hours at Flexip
and then I increased and increased and I
eventually started working full-time for
them and I had it um besides doing all
of that I also built games and I we can
talk about that in a minute but I always
uh built my games on the side. I had a
full-time job with 40 hours and I also
needed to finish my master thesis and
that all didn't work out very well in
timewise. So, um I had to at one point
just to say stop and uh quit the job at
Flexibits even though it was hard
quitting there because I enjoyed working
with them very much and um especially
like I I learned so much from Kent
especially uh he's the the technical
brain behind uh behind Fantastical and
um those years were super valuable for
me. So, it was hard to quit there, but I
knew I had to just um do something to
finally finish off my master thesis.
Yeah. So, and then did you did you
finish that? I did finish that. Yeah. I
Nice. Well, congratulations. Yes. Thank
you. And so, but during that time that
you were working there, like you
mentioned, you were you were releasing
games. Yes. And I think like at least my
understanding from following you is that
they were all like games of some sort,
right?
you
app, but you have uh
like subwords, letter rooms, ancient
board games, collection, study snacks.
Uh all of these are kind of like
interactive puzzle game and word game
kind of things. Is that an accurate
Yeah. uh explanation of the general like
style? Yeah, most most of them are. So
that's basically the my my main focus
especially um letter rooms and subwords
are uh those quiz type of games or or
yeah quiz type of games is probably the
best explanations and elementary minute
before that um also quiz type of game.
Um I had asymmetric in in the meantime
um or in between this was my second game
which was a puzzle game which didn't
work out well. So that Oh really? Like
it didn't work in the sense that it
didn't make much money or not a lot of
people used it. Um so people who played
it actually enjoyed it but not a lot of
people played it. So yeah, only to this
date have like I don't know 1,000
downloads or something like that for
that game. And just like context at the
sort of top level, you building these
games, was the
idea that you eventually kind of liked
the idea of going indie and you were
trying to build a business or was this
just a creative expression like fun
thing? So it was obviously a little
both, but it was kind of both things. So
in the ideal world, I definitely always
wanted to go indie with my games. So
that was always like kind of the main
goal, but I knew um also from France
that the game business is hard. Um yes,
um not the the easiest business to be
in, you can also see it right now that
um with people getting laid off left and
right and the the and the conditions
that people who actually work in those
companies are still sometimes under. um
like game business is not the easiest
one. So I always build my my apps and
games uh with native technologies. Um so
with Objective C, Swift UI kit, Swift
UI, Sprite Kit and stuff like that. So I
did that uh because of two reasons. one
is um because that way I can make them
as accessible as possible and the second
reason is also accessible in the uh
like disability accessibility features
sense not obviously it's less accessible
other platforms uh compared to like
Unity or something but I I wanted to to
create the best experience for those
games and apps on a limited platform but
then still even though I can only focus
on iOS. I wanted to make it really good
there instead of making it for iOS,
Android, and other platforms and then
have a meh experience across the board.
So, yeah. And like sort of at a business
level, you know, uh with elementary
minute, it your distribution model was
Apple promoting it basically, right?
Like that's how it was getting all of
its users. Yeah. So your second app or
game, no matter how good it was, if your
entire distribution model was based on
Apple featuring it, if Apple doesn't
feature it for whatever reason, because
of internal reasons. Yeah. Uh it's like
you have nothing. So throughout all
these games as you're building them, did
you start building up
uh sort
of marketing, whatever you want to call
it, mechanisms for how do you get this
to people, which maybe the answer is you
kept doing Apple, but you found out how
better to make sure Apple distribution
was consistent or were there other sort
of methods that you were learning
through all these apps? I think uh
definitely it was mostly Apple and
getting to learn how to better do that.
And I think with the art of fauna I um
kind of figured it out how it work how
it works. Yeah, I have I have a long
list of uh it seemed like you you have a
good playbook that you played out with
the Art of Fona, which is why I asked
that question because I'm like I guess
you were sort of learning that through
all of these through all of these apps.
Yeah. But you it's always um I mean even
though something works out it uh and I
have that playbook um even I if I apply
it again it can still happen that
because of some reasons it doesn't work
out with Apple because yeah it's a
higher risk. Yeah, it's definitely a
higher risk, but um also I definitely
got integrated in the whole community
more. So I um have more people reposting
about it on social media. I know how to
better do social media. I have people
who are fan of my games and apps that I
did over the years that come back to the
new stuff. So, it's basically building
up on the success of the previous games
and then hoping that people will return
for the next one. And that kind of
worked out well for the other fun. Yeah,
that makes sense. And also, I guess to
the point of making them with native
code and making them specifically for
Apple platforms. That is another uh
quiver in the arrow on getting Apple to
want to promote it cuz they want to
promote very Applecentric using Apple
technologies type type apps. Yeah, that
makes sense. So I guess uh let's like
kind of kick off the the actual the art
of fauna process. So I have a lot of
questions about the actual like I said
the business side of promoting it but
the the app itself where did that or
game itself where did that idea come
from? Like how did it kind of come into
being? Yeah. Um, so the the first time I
had the idea for the auto founder was
from just stupidly scrolling through
Instagram and then getting um because
I'm following a bunch of nature um
profiles and fe um stuff like that. I
got um suggested the profile of the
biodiversity heritage library which is a
project based I think in the US it's
mainly sponsored by the Smithsonian or
hosted by the Smith Smithsonian and um
this organization scans in uh old books
and then makes them available online for
free. So um those are old books from so
not any old book but old books that
feature um drawings of animals and
plants and stuff like that and they had
this Instagram feed where they had they
just posted different old drawings of
animals and I got one suggested for one
of those animals and it was super
beautiful and I clicked on the profile
and I couldn't stop scrolling there. So
that yeah it's a very now that you say
that it's like
uh what were what are those people
called that are not necessarily
scientists but people who catalog like
specimens. Uh it's it's good good
question. Darwin was really big on that,
right? Like that was one of his things.
Yeah. Uh but but there's a very specific
like vibe to that. Those scient
pseudocientific drawings, they're always
on parchment. So the paper has that sort
of sepiaone. I now that you're saying
that out loud, I did not put that
together that that is the artifana
style, but that is exactly Oh, that's
cool. That's cool. These are I mean
these are really they they were used
back then in the time um by scientists
to study those animals because um yeah,
I don't want to say it's not scientists.
I mean like uh it it was like a a
community. That's the word I'm looking
for. Like I feel like a lot of them were
just
like a lot a lot of them were scientists
but there was also a bunch of them that
were just quirky people who that was
their hobby. Yeah. Yeah. Definitely.
Also, but yeah, we I mean there there
are artists like um John Gul is one guy
where I have a bunch of uh images in
there and he did expeditions with Darwin
and also to Wow. um he he did an
expedition to Australia and made I think
five or six books about the animals in
Australia and drew them and um those
drawings are now heavily featured in the
art of fauna because they're super
beautiful and they are uh just they're
to use for free because the people are
long dead and it's their copyright has
long expired. I didn't realize that
those were sourced like that. Okay,
interesting. Yeah. And I so my I just so
so coming back to the Instagram feed, I
just scrolled through them and I
bookmark I think 200 images at that time
just to look at them and didn't even
think of making something out of that.
And then I realized when looking at the
dates when they were drawn that they
were drawn a long time ago and that I
could potentially use them. And back at
that time I was deep into um like puzzle
games both physical ones but also um
there was the the game patterned on
Apple Arcade. Then also um I I like
those I I was deep into um Alba um I
think Alba it's called from the the
people who made uh Monument Valley
um which was that cozy nature game where
you just run around the island and uh
explore freely and listen to the nice
animal sounds. And both those games kind
of inspired me to do something similar
where I used those old uh drawings um
that were just sitting there for free
and uh make a puzzle game around that.
And that's basically how the whole idea
started. That's interesting. So it
wasn't the mechanic that came first. No,
it was the it was the vibe. Yes. Uh,
first it's like the combination of these
old drawings that were inspiring and
just nice and pleasing looking and the
sort of cozy game style, not even
necessarily puzzle cozy games. Obviously
patterned is, but like Alba is not,
right? No, Alba is Yeah. And then you
you thought, okay, how can I take these
two elements plus your house style and
what you know and make something out of
that? Yeah. And it's interesting. It's
the first time it worked out like this
because otherwise I always come from the
gameplay side or from the game ahead.
Yeah. Yeah. So, um yeah, was interesting
how that just came to be. But um I
mentioned earlier that I'm deep into u
making things accessible and very
interested about that. I wrote also my
master thesis on game accessibility. I'm
giving a talk about game accessibility
next week at the Arctic Conference and
stuff like that. So, um, don't bring
that up right now. I'm I'm in pre FOMO.
I guess when this releases that will
either be happening at the time or have
already happened, but uh, man, I wanted
to go to that one so bad. But anyway,
yeah, Arctic Comp. Uh, I guess buy
tickets for next year cuz it's too late
now.
I want it to happen again so I can go.
Yeah, you should definitely go next
year. I think it's going to be a blast.
Yeah. Yeah. Uh, so I'm deep into
accessibility and I um my main focus is
in voiceover accessibility and making it
accessible to blind people and making a
visual puzzle game isn't very easy to
make it accessible to blind people. So,
I always have that one rule in there
that if I can't make it accessible as I
want to, then I'm not going to build the
app. So, uh found a first I had this
idea, but I stopped working for it for a
little while because I couldn't figure
out how to make it accessible. And then
I had the idea of like if you go to
Seuss or to to museums, you often have
um an animal or an animal drawing and
next to it a text about that animal, a
description about it. And I thought um
instead of having that next to each
other, I just put the text on the back
side of the puzzle or of the of the
drawing so that you um can either solve
the puzzle through um solving the
painting or it's like putting the the
painting back together or you can uh
press a button and flip it and then uh
put the text back together and that way
I had something uh that could work. Oh,
interesting. blind people because they
could just use the text site to actually
play the game. And so it's almost like a
separate game then in that sense, right?
In kind in that sense kind of a separate
game because um the one side is like
this relaxing um really basically
relaxing game um where you can just uh
put your mind off and put that thing
back together. And the other side is you
have to read through the text a couple
of times to bring the sentence in
sentences in the correct order again. So
um it's kind of different game. The one
is more like a traditional puzzle game.
The other one is more like a word game.
And yeah, um but having those two sides
made it possible to um both have the the
accessibility support but also um when
showing it to people, many people
enjoyed it to play on the text site
because they learned something about the
animal. And yeah, exactly. And you could
always uh switch back and forth. So, uh,
you could play on the image side for a
bit and then to the text side and the
back to the image side, whatever is
easier for you at that moment. Um, and
yeah, that was just a nice thing that
happened out of the the main goal of
making it accessible to blind people.
And that's really cool. Yeah. Yeah. I
like I didn't even realize that was in
the game. I've only done the the sort of
image side which let's talk about that
too. So the the kind of gameplay
mechanic is you have these beautiful
images like we talked about and they're
in kind of a card form um but they're
they're you know all broken up kind of
like a puzzle except unlike a puzzle
they're in clear blocks not necessarily
squares. A lot of them are rectangles,
but they're just out of order like
blocks. And you can pick up any of those
blocks and put them in the right order
and shift them around. And when you get
two blocks that are in the right order,
you get a very satisfying like sound
effect and they sort of merge together
and your brain feels very good. Uh, and
now th that block is sort of merged
together into one single and you sort of
just sort all these pieces around until
you get the image kind of completed. So,
it's sort of like a almost like a
traditional puzzle, but none of the
pieces look like puzzle pieces. Uh, and
the the interactive element of it
obviously could only be done digitally
because of all the sound effects and
everything that kind of goes with that.
Yeah.
Um, where did that mechanic come from?
It's very similar, like from a technical
perspective, it feels very similar to uh
letter rooms, right? Letter rooms is
where you have all the letters lined up
and you can pick them up and resort
them. Um, I think as a when I actually
think about it as a player, they are
totally different, but I'm thinking of
the sort of picking them up and moving
them around, it feels similar in that
way. Is that how you kind of came to
this idea? Were you taking these ideas
from your other apps? Yeah, I think I
came to that idea indirectly. So my mind
just uh when I thought of how to make a
puzzle game out of that, I just thought
of um splitting it up similar to how I
did it with letter rooms initially. I
also um done line by line. So not no um
no vertical splits. But first the first
idea was only to have horizontal splits
so that you have uh Yeah. So it's a
bunch of rectangles just stacked on top
of each other but none are side by side.
Yeah. And now that's those levels are
the the easy ones, the ones in the
beginning and then later you get
vertical splits to that. But the initial
idea was just those horizontal splits
and that is very similar to letter
rooms. So definitely inspiration coming
from there. But also it's to be honest
it's the easiest way to split up the the
image. So having if I do something like
um like actual puzzle pieces things get
a bit more complicated especially of how
to place them and then I would need
probably a stack somewhere to move uh
pieces out so that everything fits
together. So um it was both a bit the
inspiration from lad rooms but also it's
the it was the easiest way at least I
thought it was the easiest way so to
actually getting the drag and drop
mechanic done well because uh as you
said um pieces click together if they
are sorted correctly but it's um if they
are sorted correctly horizontally or
vertically they click together so you
get very obscure shapes that you have to
drag around and to drag those shapes
around and to make sure that those
shapes are put at the correct position
where the player actually thinks they
should be put um is a whole different
story. I'm still not 100% satisfied of
how my code works there, but people seem
to be happy with it and but I had to
rewrite that code of the drag and drop
mechanic I think three or four times to
bring it to and the it feels nicer than
trying to move icons around in my
control center still. I heard that.
That's what it makes me think of though
is that type of challenge, right? like
drag and drop where stuff moves out of
the way and goes in places where people
expect it is it's I'm going to guess cuz
I haven't done it but I'm going to guess
it's less of a technical challenge and
more of a design challenge in the sense
of you're making a thousand decisions.
Yeah. Yeah. Uh to try and make the right
assumption and how do you make those
decisions in a clever enough way that
you're not annoying people constantly?
Yes. Uh yeah, definitely I just find
that fascinating. Yeah. Yeah. The the
code itself is not very complicated
because it's a bunch of if statements
and loops of moving the pieces around
and stuff like that and no super
complicated algorithms behind that. But
it's still a bunch of uh shortcuts or or
decisions that need to be made at the
right point of time to actually move
something to the correct position.
Because also like you could have a shape
that's like an O where you um where just
in the middle you have you want to oh
there's a hole in the middle. There's a
hole in the middle and you want to place
a piece in there and there's a decision
in there that if the the piece is meant
to be in the hole then um the thing
doesn't move around because the player
would probably want to move it into the
hole. But if it doesn't fit into the
hole, then the thing would shift because
the player would probably want to shift
it above. So things like that, those are
there are many different tiny decisions
in there to make it work as the player
would expect and still I it's not
working 100% perfectly. So what's the
like what's the loop for for building
that out? Like obviously you're running
it a million times and running into all
these. Are you handing your phone to
people? Do you have a big group of
friends who are like, "Oh boy, here
comes Clemens." And you're like handing
them their phone and like, "All right,
do this. What do you think?" And you are
you writing down notes? Like how are you
how are you getting all of this to feel
right for as many people as you can?
Yeah, usually um in in the years before
that with all my games um I did a bunch
of uh game conferences. So in game
conferences it's um there so next to
things like there there are certain
conferences like we have in the iOS
world where you just sit down and watch
a bunch of talks but usually in those
conferences there are indie areas where
people are just exhibiting their games
and Oh interesting and I'm uh I did a
couple of those over the years where I
just stood there and just showed it to a
bunch of people and you usually I set it
up in a way that I didn't explain
anything to the people and just watch
them interact with it. And I learned so
much about how the the first interaction
clicks with people or doesn't click with
people by just watching how they would
approach it. And it's it's a super nice
way of doing it that way because the
people um who go to those conferences
sometimes like there are game
conferences where we have talks but
there are also other game conferences
where it the main focus is really just
go there and play games. So um there
will be more gamers in there who will
never come to those things again or you
will probably not meet them again. So
they are very harsh about the feedback
they give you and um but it's very good
that they are harsh and like honest
about that's what you want. Yeah, that's
value. Super valuable. So I learned a
lot about that over the years of both
how people interact with the game and
now have a like feeling of how how
people will probably interact with it.
But still, for every game, I have a
bunch of friends that I give the app to,
want to explain as little as possible to
them about the the app or the game and
see how they interact with it and just
uh buy them dinner or something like
that to force them to stick around with
me and uh or to Oh, yeah. I think I I
think uh you've given a talk where you
had pictures of you like making pasta
for people and then just being like,
"All right, come and like play my game
and uh let me watch you play my game and
treat you like a guinea pig." Yes. Uh
oh, that's interesting. I am very
interested. I I didn't I know that
people go to gamedev conferences in part
because they're like play testing. I had
never heard of the like sort of indie
showcase concept though. Yeah. Now I'm
like putting a call out to any
conference organizers uh listening.
I'm very intrigued at that same idea for
indie devs at conferences. That would be
so interesting. I'm curious what the
mechanics look like for how that works.
I mean, we won't dive into it here, but
you know, people should reach out to
you, I guess, or other
uh game devs uh because yeah, that's
really interesting. the idea of you
could bring what I assume was a kind of
demo version of your game intentionally
built for collecting feedback. Um
you could definitely do the same thing
at at a conference and I've gotten
somewhat similar experience where like
we're all handing our phones to each
other but Exactly. or you tell them and
they they're like oh and they go
download your app and then your whole
face turns red cuz you're like oh no
they're going to see you know how bad my
onboarding is and how how horrible it
is. But that feedback is often
ridiculously valuable. Exactly. Um and
creating an intentional space for that
is really cool. Yeah. Uh that's
interesting. Yeah. I'll have to poke
some of my conference organizer friends.
Yeah, definitely. Um I do know I think
literally they just tweeted about it uh
like right before we we started
recording, but iOS comp in Macedonia
Yeah. is doing
a a sort of specific
uh indie developer focused event. Um I
don't know all the details as they've
described them because they just tweeted
about it. So I don't want to like say
anything. I'm helping sponsor it and by
I I mean Revikat. Revikat is sponsoring
it. Uh so that's how I kind of know a
little bit about it. But I don't want to
I don't know. I don't want to say
something that isn't publicly known
already. But they are doing something in
this vein which I'm really really
curious to see. But I like the idea of
pulling inspiration from these sort of
gamedev conferences. Uh cuz yeah that's
an interesting idea. Yeah. Yeah. I
always advise people if they ask how I
get the best feedback to just go to
meetups or go to conferences and hand
them the phone and see reaction and see
their onboarding because like you said
it's like very painful if somebody just
gets stuck in the onboarding but uh it's
better to see that yourself and learn
from that and then make it better in
that moment than to release it out there
in the world and then get a bad review
for the onboarding or just lose a person
during the onboarding. Yeah. The worst
is the silent. You just silently lose
people and you have no idea why. Yeah.
Yeah. That's interesting. And I guess in
a similar vein, how are you getting you
said you've focused specifically like a
lot on accessibility, but specifically
on blind users? Do you have blind
friends around that you're doing the
same thing with or how are you getting
that kind of feedback because that's
something you literally can't do
yourself? Yeah. Um I mean I Over the
years, I learned how to interact with
voice over pretty good. So, I have a
Yeah, I guess you close your eyes. But
it's But it's still kind something
something very different. If you
interact with a device where you know
how it looks, so you have already model
in your app how in your head how to
interact with the app, then somebody
who's blind who will never see the the
actual UI. So, um, you can never
experience it the same way then like a
blind people person would because it's
like anything else. Like if you were
just developing an iPhone app without
having ever used an iPhone. Yeah. You're
going to make things based on a lot of
assumptions that like the system has
taught you certain things, right? Yeah.
And you need to build your app knowing
that the system has taught everybody
like, "Yeah, I would prefer a back
button be at the bottom where
it
apply for uh voice over mode where it's
like if you know how to navigate the iOS
in voiceover mode, there's a bunch of
conventions that might not be intuitive
if you only ever used it in your own
app." Yeah. Um, and that's hard to like
you can spend a lot of time learning how
to use voiceover mode, but it's going to
be a hard thing to to really do without
getting the feedback from people who
live in it every day. Yeah. Yeah. And
the the main source for that is the
Apple forum. There is um Yeah, this
forum I'll I'll make sure that's in the
show notes. Yeah, definitely do. Um, it
was almost closed down last year because
I was about to say, didn't that wasn't
that like at threat of being shut down
cuz the original creator was like they
didn't have time for it or something?
Uh, the original creator was so totally
burned out and didn't have time to to
work on that anymore and um like in
bunch of threats it got a bit toxic and
stuff like that. So moderation was also
a problem and um the people from B my
eyes I did pick it up and are now
funding it to be run um probably I'm not
sure how the exact model is now working
but the thing is now in in
uh safe waters or however you you uh
call that and so the community continues
to exist and that thing is really the
most valuable thing to find people who
are blind to test it out. I think I had
for subwords like 50 people um I just
wrote you can so let me get the step
back for subwords I um I just posted on
the forums uh post. So hey this is my
game. I want to make it accessible for
blind people. Um here's the test flight
link. If you could join that and give me
some feedback that would be highly
appreciated. and I had 50 people reach
out and just join that and give me super
valuable feedback of how to enhance it.
and like little places um there are
certain gestures that people are
probably not aware of if they are not
using voice over and I learned about
those gestures from the people that it
would be like good that if you have uh
if you use the escape gesture that one
element is deselected again or stuff
like that
that feedback was super valuable to make
it super accessible to uh blind people
and um bunch of Those people that I met
um in the forums through uh through the
development of subwords are then uh
continued testing out my apps in the
future. And yeah, it's basically them on
test flight. I have a new game or a new
app and I ask them if they are willing
to test it out again and then sending
them a build. That's awesome. That's
Yeah, that's really really cool. Yeah.
And I I can just recommend any other
developer who wants to enhance their um
accessibility support to just write on
the the forums and there are so many
very nice people there who are willing
to help. Yeah. And I think like anytime
uh you know you're doing test flights or
anything, but this is especially true
when you're reaching out to uh like a
specific community like the blank
community. It's always got to be, you
know, like tone matters. Like you're
asking them for help. You're not I don't
know. I think sometimes people come in
demanding things or like, well, I'm
doing this for you. Why don't you do all
this free work for me? U and so being
engaged when people give you feedback,
always responding and and integrating
their feedback and thanking them. I I'll
say like I I think one of especially in
the early days whenever I was first like
building dark noise I used to always
make sure that in my test flight notes
uh anytime I added anything that was
from somebody's recommendation I would
just put in parenthesis like thanking
them. Yeah. And like so many people and
some of them are like prominent people
in the community would be like oh hey I
got mentioned in in the notes and it's
like it took so little work from me.
Yeah. Um, but just to recognize like
thanks for people, that kind of stuff
goes a long way. And like in your case,
because you're building lots of these
apps, it's like you have a community of
people that want to do this because it's
fun and you've you've encouraged them
just like they've encouraged you and it
creates kind of a little community. So
yeah. Um, yeah. Yeah, that's really
cool. That's
also I do the same thing. Every time
somebody points out a bug to me, I put
them in the actual release notes
thanking them just first name, not to to
give. Yeah. Right. There's always a
privacy kind of implication the name but
they know if I mention that I fix the
bug uh because of them they they will
going to know that and that's always a
nice thing. And I also have in my apps
always a credit where I thank the
different testers and the people who
help me out with the app. And yeah. Oh
yeah, that's a good idea. So you've
built the Autofana. You we've talked
about kind of what the app is and
everything. Um but the release of this
app felt like you had sort of really
gotten a lot of the dials dialed in very
well. It seemed like a very good release
and not just a I released it and Apple
featured it, therefore it got a lot of
press. It was like you were hitting lots
of different things. So, can you talk
about like what your strategy was for
that launch? Like what are the different
things that you did to try and help make
it as big of of a success as it ended up
being? Yeah. So, the the first thing
that I did was I created a pre-order for
the Autoona very early. So, I did um
start with the pre-order in the start of
December and um Oh, wow. Yeah, that's
like months before, right? I think 2
months before the actual release, I did
start pre-order and I then um reached
out to Apple through those uh feature
nomination forms to get featured. And in
I'm not sure if there is a section in
the in the app section, but in the game
section, there is a extra section about
uh games that are coming soon. And I got
featured in there for Oh, I didn't know
that was a thing. So, you can ask. So,
we're talking about the nomination
thing, which is now like a button in App
Store Connect. It's a lot easier to get
to. It says nominate your app, and you
can fill out a little blurb to explain
why Apple might be interested in
featuring your app, right? So, you can
do that for an app in pre-order.
Exactly. To sort of to nominate them
promoting the pre-order. Yes. Oh,
fascinating. Okay. I didn't know that.
And if you go to the games tab, there's
definitely some app that is currently u
promoted down in the section of games
that are coming soon, but also up with
the huge banner. So, I also got the
feature up there um with the other fauna
with uh um where they promoted it that
it's going to come out soon and that got
me like
6,500 pre-orders over the two months by
the time it launched at the time it
launched. And that that's a lot. That's
a lot. And that's uh the the good thing
here is that um everybody who pre-orders
it um the the app is going to be
downloaded to their device on the the
exact same on the same day. So it's to
the algorithm similar to or the same
thing as if they would have clicked that
download button on that exact date. and
I um having the pre-order I could
promote it a couple of times on Twitter.
Apple picked it up through the featuring
and stuff like that. So I had these big
chunk of people who are interested in
the app but they also got it downloaded
at the exact same date. So the uh the
algorithm and the charts
uh the chart position was pretty good
for other founder on the very first day
which then also generated more
downloads. So that was which all of that
helps your ASO and all of those you know
businessy things as well
and that thing definitely helped a lot.
I had also bunch of people who were
testing out uh the art of founder over
test flight before um the actual release
and they were super kind and to post
about the art of founder upon release.
So I think I get got so many shout outs
from the community on the launch date
which uh were was like super satisfying
and super like mindboggling to me. Um
especially like I'm friends with with
couple of people like Yordi or Ha um now
but a couple of years ago I was just
following them on Twitter and was like
impressed by their work and they are now
actually posting about my app or my my
game that I released. So things like
that just mind-blowing and just just
super nice and that yeah worked out very
well on the social media side. And um
additionally what I also did is the the
app is a free download. So you can play
the first 10 puzzles and after the
seventh puzle after you solve that you
have a pretty good feeling for the game.
So if you're stuck um with the game for
that time, then you're kind of invested
in it, but it's also far enough away
from the pay wall that you're not um if
you So after the seventh parcel, I asked
the person to give a rating and um if
the pay wall would come up right after
that, then they would probably be
annoyed and then change the rating
again. But it's uh having it at that
position worked out very well. that many
people rated the app very early on. And
I think I'm now at around 2,200
uh ratings, 40 games after 1 month of
the release, which is like more than all
of my other apps and games combined,
which is insane. But it's Does that Does
that correlate directly to number of
downloads or is that something unique to
the rating request like timing that you
have? Do you think I think it's uh
definitely with the timing and with
really Oh, that's interesting kind of
game cuz my thought was almost like I
guess it depends
but I guess it's better to have it a
number of puzzles in than it to be like
the number of times you open the app cuz
there's probably a decent amount of
people that
download it, play through the free
puzzles, and then never, you know, touch
it again. Uh, and so having it like
you've gotten a couple free things,
you're more likely to give a positive
rating, but you still want to, generally
speaking, the advice is like it's still
better to ask for a rating than to not.
Uh, so you don't want to overprovision
on just the do only do it at a positive
time. It's better to show it to them
early, but in your case, it's like,
yeah, if you if you've made it through a
couple puzzles, you're probably going to
be more likely to leave a rating. Ah,
that's Yeah, that's really interesting.
What were the other like in your other
apps? How did you usually do the rating
prompt? I also like in in subwords it's
in in studies next for example it's um
based on like I think either they have
um used it for um solving a bunch of
lessons in one session or after they
entered in the app for the for time or
something like that. So, and then
completing a learning session correctly.
And not sure how it was for the ancient
board game collection for letter rooms,
it's also after solving a bunch of
puzzles, but probably too late. So, I
need to adjust that a bit. So, yeah. So,
with the art of fauna, you think the big
kind of differentiator is basically you
you being more likely to ask, whether
it's earlier or
uh whatever. It's it's at a phase where
more people are going to be prompted.
Yes. And interesting. Um, and it is at a
point where they got a more difficult
level for the first time or second time
they got a bit more different level uh
difficult level. So they just uh made it
through something that was a bit more
challenging and they feel even bit more
rewarded. So they're um kind of more
likely to give you a positive rating
because they have that nice feeling of
having made it through that puzzle. So,
I did find the sweet spot for
that kind of accidentally, but also I
now have like a good feeling about where
to to place that thing. And that
definitely helped a lot with um like
getting um with my ASO and getting the
the algorithm to pick up the app uh
better. And then also uh every time I
hit the milestone with my ratings, I
could make a social media post out of
that and then throw it on Twitter and
Blue Sky and the Instagram channel of
Founder and then uh get more people
reposting that one and then again people
picking that that I think was one of the
things that it felt like you did really
good this time which is that sort of uh
join me in celebrating this this thing's
success.
uncomfort. But the reality is, and I
mean the reality is there are a small
number of people that will get annoyed
and that's the part that's hard. But the
majority of people, I think, at least
certainly me, I get excited. I like
following other people's success. I find
it really inspiring. Yeah. Um, and it's
just fun. And each one of those is a
reminder. Like, I bet you I missed one
of your original announcements of the
pre-order going up or whatever. But
whenever you said something like, "Oh my
gosh, I crossed, you know, 100
pre-orders or whatever," I probably saw
that and I was like, "Oh shoot, he has a
new app coming out." Like, that's pretty
cool. Especially in today's hyperfrured
social media world, like you can't
assume everybody's going to see
everybody. Almost nobody is a Twitter
completionist like in the old days. Uh
so it really I don't know, maybe a lot
of people are going to disagree right in
if you do. Uh, but like I really think
there's a huge benefit to the community,
not even just yourself, but also to
yourself if you are publicly celebrating
your wins, uh, where things are. And I
do think if you're wanting to be
genuine, uh, the other side to that is
publicly talking about when things don't
go well. Um, adding qualifiers, not
being disingenuous about the why for
things. Yeah. uh because that that can
be easy to do as well. But um but yeah,
I I love I I've mentioned on the show
before, but whenever I kind of first got
into this racket uh was right after
Jordan Morgan finally released uh his
spin stacks app that he had been working
on for forever. And I just was super
inspired by how like extraordinarily
public he was with everything, numbers,
everything as it happened. And I've sort
of followed that whole mentality and I
feel like it served me super well. Yeah.
Um, and with the Art of Fauna in
particular, I felt like I was really
following you in that journey through
social media, not just, you know,
because like we know each other. Um, and
I I think that helps build this kind of
momentum and increases chances that
anybody's going to potentially pick that
up on the press side. Yeah, definitely.
And I think that was also um like having
the pre-order be so early, having the
two months of getting people excited for
the actual release that definitely
contributed to and yeah, like you said,
if I just post about the app one time
when it releases or on the next day
after the release, it's very easy to
miss at these days. So, I um just
recently a friend of mine released an
app and I didn't see it that it was
already out there just because it's I'm
I'm on holiday. I'm not looking at um
Twitter that often so it's easy to miss.
Yeah. Yep. Exactly. Yeah. And really
quick, uh, and then I promise I'll try
to wrap this up because I know we're
already reaching kind of time, but, um,
I've also noticed kind of on the past
the launch side of things, um, it looks
like you've been
posting sort of like Tik Tok style
videos, I don't know if it's actually
even on TikTok. I don't remember where
I've seen them, but vertical videos with
what sounds like kind of that standard
AI voice. uh that's like popular and not
cheesy or I guess it is cheesy but you
know what I mean it's that's like the
that's the house style or whatever. Um
that's sort of showing off fauna. What's
what's the story with that and how is
has that worked out for you? Um it did
work
out okayish I would say. I think um it's
I posted it on on Instagram and on on
Tik Tok and also uh tried to post one or
two of those on Reddit and um other
social media platforms and um it worked
out fine. I got some people who who then
learned about certain parts of the app
that they didn't know about it. Um, but
I think it was definitely valuable for
me to do as also to get more into
editing and be better at that. And so
you built those? Yeah, I did build
those. So what did you use for that? So
for for the initial for the app preview,
I have um Final Cut lying around. Um
Okay. And uh used that. But for the the
latest two videos, I used uh Reveo. I
think Reveo it's spoken out. Let me
check. Um, I'll include I'll include a
link in the in the show notes as well. I
was mostly curious just because like
Yeah, it's funny. It's not like it was
over hyper polished or something, but it
had that like like I said like that
house style of these
vertical mobile game like promo ad
things and so I was curious like what
you use for that like even just the
voice like that it stood out to me.
Yeah. Yeah. the there is on in the so
one videos of those I made with the Tik
Tok editor and that is the basic Tik Tok
voice in there. Okay. But uh Rio has um
has also bunch of different voices and
one is called David uh and he's an UK
old male guy which sounds like David
Edinburghough and that is ah that's yeah
that's perfect
fora yeah for the art of fauna. So, I
used that for the latest video and even
though it didn't get a lot of uh
attention the video, it was just super
fun to make and I definitely will you're
doing those.
That's awesome. All right. Well, uh we
are we are approaching the end here. So,
uh I will end by asking the question
that I always ask to end the show, which
is
uh which is uh what's a person or people
out there that have inspired you that
you'd recommend others check out?
So, um I prepared for this question and
um it's I mean I have a bunch of people
lined up there who I'm not going to uh
talk more about because there are
episodes with them of the launch podcast
like uh like Leo Yordi or Ha. Um
especially Ha's work I've been following
for a while now and I'm always impressed
with with the things that he does. So
definitely worth checking him out. Um
then also um I really enjoy the work of
Andy Allen from um the not boring apps
because
I think he definitely does uh things
differently and like just pushes the
boundaries of what apps can look like
and feel like especially like um much of
the sound design and haptic design that
I did. Oh yeah, we didn't even get into
that. uh we won't talk about it, but
yeah, if you haven't already downloaded
Artifa, uh well, for one, what are you
doing? But do it just to experience the
like like the cozy vibes, the sound
design of as you're moving things
around, the kind of constant ambient
sound. It's just chef's guest. It's
very, very, very good. Thank you. I had
help with that by Josh Moy who also did
sound effects for um for Fantastical for
example or flighty and many famous apps.
So he's really really good at what he
does and um made the the sound design
there but I definitely was inspired by
the work from uh from Andy at the not
boring apps. Yeah. And so definitely
follow what he's doing because it's very
interesting. I need I need to get him I
need to get him on the show. Uh Andy, if
you're listening, tell me.
And the the person I definitely want to
talk about is Frederick um from One
Tech. Uh who you also should get on the
show sooner or later. Um because I I met
Frederick also in 2015 at the very first
Dubdub. He was a scholar there and he is
I think the person who had the most
scholarships uh ever. So I think he was
there with five or six times um with
scholarships and so he was always around
there and we became friends over the
years. We are also um now always
traveling to adopt the DC together and
yeah I'm just very impressed what he did
with one sec especially and with um es
especially his approach about bringing
in um a scientist to study the users or
study the interaction of one sec and
that's a very different approach of how
most people build apps and how most
people like um analyze their data um
doing actual science with it and that
all all things that he did does around
one sec and also with his other apps but
um one sec in particular just fascinates
me and super amazing and you should
definitely bring it on to a show sooner
or later. Yes, he needs also if you're
listening Frederick uh call me. Yes, I
both of them uh have been as as I always
say on my list for a while, but I Yes, I
definitely need to make that happen.
Yes, you should.
Awesome. Well, those are those are uh
excellent picks. Uh I appreciate that.
And yes, everybody should be following
all of those people uh uh and like
checking out their apps cuz
yeah, especially that group. I feel like
it's there's certain people who are good
to follow online because they're sharing
lots of advice and stuff and then
there's other people where yes that's
true but also it's just like just
download their apps
and like tinker and play with them to uh
to try and solve a problem like I was
I'll just pitch it really quick because
you know this is my show and I can abuse
it but I just released a Mac app uh
called Frameus. You should go download
it. Uh, but I had never built a Mac app
before
and it's slightly embarrassing how much
time I spent analyzing Helm uh uh by Ha
and Paul uh who also I haven't had on.
Maybe I should just have both of them on
to talk about Helm because that almost
deserves its own episode. But anyway,
that Mac app is just a great Mac app and
it's in the Mac App Store so I know it's
all stuff that you can do. Uh cuz the
Mac's always weird because there's like
who how many people are hacking things
or whatever and just like being able to
just play around and see how people
solved different problems or what they
did uh is super inspiring. And that list
like Leo, Yordi, Ha, Andy, and
Frederick, it's like all their apps are
just very solid thought through all the
details type apps uh that they that they
all make. And so yeah, that's a good
list. Yeah.
Cool. Well, um I guess I'll I'll go
ahead and land the plane here. So, where
can people find you and your work? Um on
I'm on basically all the social media
sites that are now around. So, um on
Blue Sky mostly, so I post most of the
stuff there, but I also cross-ost the
other founder stuff on Twitter. I have
um also Masterone channel that I should
use more often and um I have a website
uh which is uh straasa.app. You can link
on that um which lists up all my apps
there and yeah live journal uh handle.
Um what
live journal was that not a thing? Uh is
what what's life journal? It's like pre
It's like pre MySpace. Uh
no, I'm curious if it's still around. My
uh we we had a a similar thing called
Shulafet in uh in Germany, Austria
thing. Those were my first um social
media things, but never heard of I
didn't actually have one. I was I was
just finding the most obscure one I
could ask for. Uh
awesome. Uh, and I guess I'll I'll try
this again here and just play it out
live instead of do a pre-recorded thing.
So, uh, this is the end of the episode.
If you want to find more Launch, you can
go to
launchedfm.com. Uh, and I also am on all
of the social media uh, that exists out
there, including the one that probably
just released tomorrow. Uh, so usually
it's launched FM or uh, just launched on
Macedon, I think, but everywhere else
it's launched FM. Blue Sky, I guess, is
launched fm.com. But yeah, you can find
me and then you can find me uh at
charliemchapman just about everywhere
except for Twitter, which is
still_chucky.
[Music]